<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata xml:lang="en">
	<Esri>
		<CreaDate>20260527</CreaDate>
		<CreaTime>11341900</CreaTime>
		<ArcGISFormat>1.0</ArcGISFormat>
		<SyncOnce>TRUE</SyncOnce>
	</Esri>
	<tool name="KMZtoOrganizedGDBWaterfall" displayname="KMZ to Organize GDB (Waterfall)" toolboxalias="kmztools" xmlns="">
		<summary>Converts KMZ/KML inputs to a clean organized Geodatabase (or N Geodatabases) using a step-by-step waterfall of choices: (1) container shape, (2) split-into-Feature-Datasets toggle, (3a) Feature Dataset source if FDs are on, and (3b) Feature Class naming strategy. Parses popup HTML into typed attribute fields, adds Folder1/2/3 columns for folder context, and projects to a chosen coordinate system. Scratch folder is auto-created next to the chosen output and kept after the run for re-use.</summary>
		<usage>Pick KMZ files and walk down the numbered questions. The downstream questions (3a, 3b) re-populate their options based on earlier answers. NetworkLink Options (collapsed) follow external KMZ references from inside source KMZs -- off by default; turn on when a source is a wrapper around live data feeds.</usage>
		<parameters>
			<param name="input_kmz" displayname="Input KMZ/KML Files" type="Required" direction="Input" datatype="File" expression="input_kmz">
				<dialogReference>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;One or more KMZ or KML files. Each becomes its own per-input scratch GDB internally; the scratch folder is created automatically next to the chosen output (see "Output Geodatabase" or "Output Folder" depending on your container choice in 1).&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</dialogReference>
			</param>
			<param name="container" displayname="1. Output container" type="Required" direction="Input" datatype="String" expression="container">
				<dialogReference>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;Where the converted features end up. This is the first decision and it shapes everything downstream.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;ONE MERGED GDB -- All input KMZs combined into a single Geodatabase that you pick under "Output Geodatabase". Best for cross-source analysis and when the dataset is meant to live together.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;ONE GDB PER SOURCE KMZ -- Each input KMZ produces its own separate Geodatabase file inside the folder you pick under "Output Folder". Best when each KMZ is a separate deliverable, or when input KMZs have unrelated schemas you don't want merged. The subsequent questions (2, 3a, 3b) still apply -- they determine the FD/FC layout INSIDE each per-KMZ GDB. The only restriction is that the "Source KMZ filename" FD source (3a) is hidden since the GDB itself already represents the source.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;This choice affects which output picker is enabled and which Feature Dataset source options (3a) are available.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</dialogReference>
			</param>
			<param name="output_gdb" displayname="Output Geodatabase (used when container is 'One merged GDB')" type="Optional" direction="Output" datatype="Workspace" expression="output_gdb">
				<dialogReference>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;Path to the file Geodatabase you want to create. Required when container (1) is "One merged GDB"; disabled otherwise.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;If the GDB already exists, the tool refuses to overwrite -- delete it (or pick a new path) before running. A scratch folder is auto-created at &amp;lt;parent&amp;gt;\&amp;lt;stem&amp;gt;_scratch\ to hold intermediate per-KMZ GDBs and is kept after the run.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</dialogReference>
			</param>
			<param name="output_folder" displayname="Output Folder (used when container is 'One GDB per source KMZ')" type="Optional" direction="Output" datatype="Folder" expression="output_folder">
				<dialogReference>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;Folder that will receive one Geodatabase per source KMZ. Required when container (1) is "One GDB per source KMZ"; disabled otherwise.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;Each output GDB is named after its source (e.g. ProjectA.gdb, HazardsReport.gdb). Scratch GDBs land in &amp;lt;folder&amp;gt;\_scratch\ inside the chosen folder and are kept after the run.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</dialogReference>
			</param>
			<param name="split_fds" displayname="2. Split output into Feature Datasets?" type="Required" direction="Input" datatype="Boolean" expression="split_fds">
				<dialogReference>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;Whether each Feature Class lives inside a Feature Dataset (FD), or at the Geodatabase root.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;CHECKED (default) -- FCs are organized inside FDs. Choose what becomes the FD name in 3a. The FC naming strategy in 3b shows options that work with FDs.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;UNCHECKED -- No FDs. FCs sit at the GDB root. Question 3a is ignored; 3b shows root-level naming strategies instead.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;Folder1, Folder2, Folder3 attribute columns are populated in either case (except when the FC naming strategy is "Leaf folder name", which encodes the leaf in the FC name itself).&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</dialogReference>
			</param>
			<param name="fd_source" displayname="3a. Feature Dataset source (only used if FDs are on)" type="Optional" direction="Input" datatype="String" expression="fd_source">
				<dialogReference>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;How the Feature Dataset name is derived. Only used when "Split output into Feature Datasets?" (2) is checked.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;TOP FOLDER -- The third-from-deepest folder segment becomes the FD name (notation: segments[-3]). Example: a placemark in folder "Birds 2026 / BUOW / Known" yields FD "Birds_2026". Use when your KMZ is organized as "Category / Subcategory / Leaf" and you want one FD per Category.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;TOP TWO FOLDERS COMBINED -- The two folders above the leaf are joined (notation: segments[-3] + segments[-2]). Example: "Birds 2026 / BUOW / Known" yields FD "Birds_2026_BUOW". Use for finer FD grouping when Category alone is too broad.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;SOURCE KMZ FILENAME -- One FD per source KMZ file. Only available when container (1) is "One merged GDB" (in the per-KMZ container the GDB IS the source -- redundant). Best for traceability: the FD name tells you which KMZ a feature came from.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;For folder paths shorter than 3 levels, the strategy falls back gracefully to whatever top segment is available.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</dialogReference>
			</param>
			<param name="fc_naming" displayname="3b. Feature Class naming strategy" type="Required" direction="Input" datatype="String" expression="fc_naming">
				<dialogReference>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;How each Feature Class is named. The available options change based on whether FDs are split (2).&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;PER-GEOMETRY ONLY -- "Points", "Polylines", "Polygons". Minimal naming; relies on the FD name (3a) and Folder1/2/3 attribute columns for context. Always available.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;LEAF FOLDER NAME -- The leaf folder becomes the FC (e.g. "Known", "Suspected"). When two leaves in the same FD share a name across geometries, a geometry suffix is auto-added. Only available when 2 is checked AND 3a is "Top two folders combined".&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;LEAF + GEOMETRY -- FC name = &amp;lt;leaf&amp;gt;_&amp;lt;geom&amp;gt; (e.g. "Known_Points", "Suspected_Polygons"). Predictable: the geometry suffix is always visible. Good middle-ground when you want one FC per leaf but cleanly separated by geometry.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;PARENT + LEAF + GEOMETRY -- FC name = &amp;lt;parent&amp;gt;_&amp;lt;leaf&amp;gt;_&amp;lt;geom&amp;gt; (e.g. "BUOW_Known_Points"). Most folder context preserved in the FC name.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;FOLDER PAIR + GEOMETRY -- FC name = &amp;lt;top&amp;gt;_&amp;lt;parent&amp;gt;_&amp;lt;geom&amp;gt; (e.g. "Birds_2026_BUOW_Points"). The leaf moves into the Folder3 column. Best for compact symbology grouping when leaves are repetitive.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;TOP FOLDER + GEOMETRY (only when 2 is unchecked) -- FC name = &amp;lt;top&amp;gt;_&amp;lt;geom&amp;gt; (e.g. "Birds_2026_Points"). All leaves under a top folder collapse into one FC, distinguished by Folder3 attribute.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;If a resulting FC name exceeds the 64-character file-GDB limit, the leading folder portion is shortened automatically while the geometry suffix (e.g. "_Polygons") stays intact.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</dialogReference>
			</param>
			<param name="output_sr" displayname="Output Coordinate System" type="Required" direction="Input" datatype="String" expression="output_sr">
				<dialogReference>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;Target spatial reference for the output. Scratch GDBs are always WGS 1984; geometries project to this SR during Phase 2 and FDs/FCs are created in it.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;SHORTLIST: WGS 1984 (pass-through); NAD 1983 HARN State Plane Washington N/S (US Ft); Oregon N/S (Intl Ft); California I-VI (US Ft); NAD 1983 UTM Zones 9N-12N (m).&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;TRANSFORMATION (auto-applied): HARN State Plane uses a 2-step chain WGS84 -- NAD83 -- HARN_state. UTM NAD83 uses a single step WGS84 -- NAD83. WGS 1984 applies no transformation.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;KMZ source accuracy is typically ~5 m; pick the SR for your project deliverable, not the source data. Survey-grade work should not be sourced from KMZ.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</dialogReference>
			</param>
			<param name="follow_network_links" displayname="Follow NetworkLinks" type="Optional" direction="Input" datatype="Boolean" expression="follow_network_links">
				<dialogReference>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;If on, the converter follows &amp;lt;NetworkLink&amp;gt; elements in source KMZs and downloads the referenced external KMZ/KML files inline. Useful for KMZs that are just wrappers around remote datasets (e.g. live database queries via Google Earth's NetworkLink mechanism). Off by default to avoid surprise network calls.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</dialogReference>
			</param>
			<param name="network_link_max_depth" displayname="NetworkLink Max Depth" type="Optional" direction="Input" datatype="Long" expression="network_link_max_depth">
				<dialogReference>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;How many levels of nested NetworkLinks to recurse. 1 = follow only the direct links in the source. 2 = also follow links found inside downloaded NetworkLink targets. Default 2. Ignored when "Follow NetworkLinks" is off.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</dialogReference>
			</param>
			<param name="network_link_timeout" displayname="NetworkLink Download Timeout (seconds)" type="Optional" direction="Input" datatype="Long" expression="network_link_timeout">
				<dialogReference>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;Per-link HTTP timeout for NetworkLink downloads. Default 30 seconds. Increase on slow networks or when fetching large remote KMZs. Ignored when "Follow NetworkLinks" is off.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</dialogReference>
			</param>
		</parameters>
	</tool>
</metadata>
